Finding Aid for Lincoln Highway Association Records, 1911-1941
University of Michigan Library (Special Collections Research Center)
Lincoln Highway Association Records 1911-1941 1912-1930
Lincoln Highway Association
6 linear ft. and 1 portfolio
THC-LHA
Formed in 1913 by Carl G. Fisher, Frank A. Seiberling, and Henry B. Joy, the Lincoln Highway Association was made up of representatives from the automobile, tire, and cement industries. The Association aimed to plan, fund, construct, and promote the first transcontinental highway in North America. The route ran from New York to San Francisco, and covered approximately 3,400 miles. The Detroit headquarters of the Association closed in 1928. This collection contains: correspondence, particularly between members of the Association and government officials; meeting minutes; reports, bulletins, and newsletters published by the Association; motorist maps of the route; and annotated editions of The Complete Official Road Guide of the Lincoln Highway. Photographs from the Lincoln Highway Association Records have been digitized and are accessible online at the Lincoln Highway Digital Image Collection (http://quod.lib.umich.edu/l/linchigh). The Digital Image Collection contains over 3,000 images including views of construction underway, towns and cities, markers, bridges, cars, camp sites, scenic views, and snapshots of Association directors and field secretaries traveling the route.
University of Michigan Library (Special Collections Research Center)
Donated by Gael Hoag and H.C. Ostermann in 1937.
The collection is open for research.
The majority of the photographs from the original archive have been rehoused and digitized. They may be viewed at the Lincoln Highway Digital Image Collection.
The Lincoln Highway Association formed in July 1913 for the purposes of building the first transcontinental highway in North America. The idea was promoted by Carl G. Fisher beginning in September 1912 under the name "The Coast-to-Coast Rock Highway". Fisher was behind the creation and paving of the Indianapolis Motor Speedway and the organization of the first Indianapolis 500 in 1911. He founded the Prest-O-Lite Company, which made carbide headlights for automobiles. Fisher promoted his idea among other businessmen in the automobile industry. He felt that the highway would promote business as well as provide citizens with an enjoyable route throughout the towns and countryside.
Fisher's 1912 estimate for the gravel highway was ten million dollars. Funds would be used to purchase materials with the idea that labor and machinery would be provided by the municipalities the route passed through. Fisher's fundraising efforts were an immediate success. He gained support from the automobile industry as different companies pledged to support one percent of their revenues' to the highway. Donations by individuals in the amount of five dollars also began to arrive. Men such as Frank A. Seiberling of the Goodyear Tire Company and Henry B. Joy of the Packard Motor Car Company were influential in gaining more support from the automobile industry, despite the fact that Henry Ford and the Ford Motor Company refused to support the project.
Briefly located in Indianapolis, the headquarters of the Lincoln Highway Association settled in Detroit, Michigan. In July 1913 the Lincoln Highway Association was incorporated and the group of businessmen exclaimed their purpose, "To procure the establishment of a continuous improved highway from the Atlantic to the Pacific, open to lawful traffic of all description without toll charges: such highway to be known, in memory of Abraham Lincoln, as 'The Lincoln Highway.'" The proposed highway was named after Lincoln to honor the fallen president as well as to appeal to American citizens' sense of patriotism and thereby gain support and funding for the project. The new board of directors began planning the route of the highway, beginning in New York City and ending in San Francisco, California. The goal was to find the shortest route from coast to coast while passing through towns and scenic locations to provide an enjoyable drive.
Throughout its history, the Association was organized and administered by businessmen from the automobile industry. The group ran many public events to gain support for the highway and awarded donations with certificates, membership cards, and pins. A system of consuls was developed in order to help manage the situation and communication regarding the highway along the route. The board appointed one consul for each state who in turn named consuls for various counties and towns. The consul system also enabled more people to become involved in the operations of the Association.
When completed, the route ran through twelve states including: New York, New Jersey, Pennsylvania, Ohio, Illinois, Iowa, Nebraska, Wyoming, Utah, Nevada, and California and spanned approximately 3,400 miles. The route was strenuous and some areas were still treacherous to pass by automobile. The Lincoln Highway Association began constructing "seedling miles," or paved sections, along the route with the support of the cement and steel companies. The Association hoped this would create more support and demand for the Lincoln Highway as well as increase its use and value. The construction of "seedling miles" halted in 1919 when the Association felt the public was fully behind the construction of paved roadways.
The route underwent slight changes to make it more direct as well as easier to pass. Several sections of the route received considerably more attention than others including the "Ideal" Section in Indiana and what became known as the Seiberling Section through Utah and Nevada. The highway throughout Utah and Nevada was a concern as the sparse population, poor infrastructure, and inhospitable geography made travel difficult.
In July 1919, Henry C. Ostermann embarked on the first Army Transcontinental Motor Convoy across the Lincoln Highway accompanied by seventy-two vehicles and 297 men. The group included both military personal as well as civilians. The convoy was used as training, testing of military vehicles, and served as a test of the stability of the roads and bridges on the Lincoln Highway. The trip lasted sixty-two days and included numerous repairs on military vehicles as well as the rebuilding of bridges that did not support the heavy loads. The convoy was successful in convincing the military that paved roads were essential to the country's national defense. In turn, federal funding for paved highways exploded.
In 1922 the Association began construction on the "Ideal" Section between Schererville and Dyer, Indiana. This 1.3 mile stretch had concrete paving ten inches thick and allowed up to four lanes of traffic with its forty foot width. The section was illuminated for night driving. The "Ideal" Section was yet another tactic by the Lincoln Highway Association to gain support and use for improvement of their route. It was during this time that the Lincoln Highway began competing with other transcontinental routes for attention, money, and use.
By 1925 the Federal Highway System was well developed and numbered routes east-west as well as north-south covered the map. The prominence of the federal system lead to a decline for named highways, including the Lincoln Highway. Portions of the Lincoln Highway were marked with numbered federal routes at this time.
The Lincoln Highway Association officially disbanded at the end of 1927 after realizing their mission to begin an intercontinental network of highways succeeded. The organization continued to have informal meetings sporadically for several subsequent years. In 1928, the Boy Scouts of America erected 3,000 markers along the route of the Lincoln Highway. The cement markers were designed by the Association and intended to keep motorist on the route. The red, white, and blue makers carried the Lincoln Highway insignia and directional arrows pointed motorists to the continuation of the route.
The Interstate Highway Act of 1956 further eroded the use of the Lincoln Highway. Routes were redirected outside of towns to decrease traffic. Interstate 80 took over as the transcontinental highway across the middle of the country. Interstate 80 runs along the same basic route as the old Lincoln Highway in many locations, but is straighter, quicker, and ultimately shorter than the original Lincoln Highway. Many portions of the Lincoln Highway lay unused and in ruins today, other portions are still used as local routes through many states, and in some areas the old, abandoned highway can be seen running alongside the current Interstate 80. Only a fraction of the original 3,000 markers remain.
Sources:
Hokanson, Drake. The Lincoln Highway: Main Street Across America. Iowa City, Iowa: University of Iowa Press. 1999.
The Lincoln Highway Association Records date from 1911 to 1993 with the bulk of materials concentrated before 1930. The records are divided into five series: Official Business (1912-1941), Correspondence (1912-1929), Planning (1914-1940), Publicity (1911-1993), Publications (1915-1935), Jens Jensen Drawings (1922-1924) and Miscellaneous.
The Lincoln Highway Association archive was donated to the University of Michigan's Transportation Library in 1937. The archive was transferred to the Special Collections Library in 1992.
Communication was frequent between members of the Association as well as with officials from towns, counties, states, and the federal government. Correspondence and meeting minutes make up an important part of the collection. The Association published reports, bulletins, and newsletters to keep board members and the public aware of the Highway's progress. Maps of the driving route along with mileages were provided for motorists for navigation as were five editions of The Complete Official Road Guide of the Lincoln Highway.
Photographs from the Lincoln Highway Association Records have been digitized and are accessible online at the Lincoln Highway Digital Image Collection (http://quod.lib.umich.edu/l/linchigh). The Digital Image Collection contains over 3,000 images including views of construction underway, towns and cities, markers, bridges, cars, camp sites, scenic views, and snapshots of Association directors and field secretaries traveling the route.
Subjects:
Bement, Austin.; Chapin, Roy D. (Roy Dikeman), 1880-1936.; Fisher, Carl G. (Carl Graham), 1874-1939.; Hoag, Gael.; Jensen, Jens, 1860-1951.; Joy, Henry B. (Henry Bourne), 1864-1936.; Ostermann, Henry C., d. 1920.; Pardington, Arthur.; Lincoln Highway Association.; Associations, organizations, etc. -- 20th century -- Indiana -- Indianapolis.; Associations, organizations, etc. -- 20th century -- Michigan -- Detroit.; Automobile travel -- United States -- 20th century.; Roads -- Esthetic considerations.; Roads -- United States -- Design and construction -- 20th century.; Roadside architecture -- United States.; Scenic byways -- United States -- 20th century.; Transportation, Automotive -- United States.; United States -- Description and travel -- 1910-; Detroit (Mich.) -- History -- 20th century.; Lincoln Highway.; Lincoln Highway -- Guidebooks.
Genre Terms:
Correspondence.; Drawings.; Logs (records).; Minutes.; Maps.; Travel guidebooks.; Photographs.
- Official Business
  The Official Business series (1912-1941) contains records relating to operational functions of the Association and consists of several subseries including Meeting Minutes, Reports, Bulletins, and Legal Documents.
  Meeting Minutes (1913-1926) contains the official meeting minutes and accompanying documents for the Board of Directors (1913-1925), Executive Committee (1923-1941), Organization Committee (1913-1915), and the Annual Meeting (1923-1926). Meeting minutes were concentrate heavily on the finances of the Lincoln Highway Association. Details of fundraising efforts and explanations of how money was spent on building costs, contractors, and so on, are present in the minutes. Meeting minutes were housed in black leather binders with "[name of the committee], Lincoln Highway Association" in gold printing. The binders are retained as artifacts and are located in Box 5.
  The Reports subseries (1914-1923) includes official reports from the Lincoln Highway Association. These include Annual Reports, Technical Committee Meeting Reports, and a number of miscellaneous reports. The purpose of the majority of reports is to describe progress on the construction of the Lincoln Highway. Some reports are specifically focused for internal organization use while others were written for the Department of Agriculture or other government bodies.
  Bulletins (1912-1926) include three main subcategories: "Bulletins from Secretary's Office," "Directors' Bulletins," and "To Directors, Officers, and Founders." The Association used these bulletins as a form of communication to provide their officials with up-to-date information regarding the activities of the organization. The changes in category stated above were different names of the same bulletin, which remained consistent in content and form. It appears that bulletins were issued on a weekly or semi-weekly basis. The typical bulletin was one to two pages in length and authored by the Secretary of the Association.
  The Legal Documents suberies (1913-1927) is a mix of internal and external records containing several varieties of documents. Founding Documents/Internal resolutions contains records pertinent to the establishment of the organization including the prospectus and incorporation papers of the Lincoln Highway Association. Internal resolutions passed by various boards within the Association are also present. Contracts/Resolutions with States includes documents from Indiana and Utah with the Association regarding the construction of the Lincoln Highway. Legislative Documents contains copies of bills from both the Senate, House of Representatives, and state governments. Financial Statements/Reports is relatively small, consisting of scattered formal financial statements. A majority of this information is out of context. For more records dealing with financial information see the Meeting Minutes subseries and the Correspondence series. Hearings/Briefs before the Secretary of Agriculture contain the transcripts and published version of a report concerning the Lincoln Highway in Utah and Nevada given on May 14, 1923.
  - Meeting Minutes
    - Board of Directors
      - July 1, 1913 (Box 1)
      - July 1, 1913-September 29, 1913 (Box 1)
      - October 27, 1913-October 6, 1914 (Box 1)
      - November 10, 1914 (Box 1)
      - December 1, 1915-November 9, 1916 (Box 1)
      - January 26, 1918 (Box 1)
      - December 30, 1918 (Box 1)
      - December 30, 1919 (Box 1)
      - April 17, 1920-December 4, 1920 (Box 1)
      - December 28, 1920 (Box 1)
      - May 27, 1921-December 28, 1921 (Box 1)
      - December 28, 1921, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - January 19, 1923 (Box 1)
      - Business Meeting, 1925 (Box 1)
    - Executive Committee
      - August 14, 1923-December 7, 1923 (Box 1)
      - January 17, 1924-December 1, 1923 (Box 1)
      - May 22, 1924-January 19, 1925 (Box 1)
      - January 21, 1925 (Box 1)
      - January 21, 1925-April 21, 1926 (Box 1)
      - April 21, 1926-October 30, 1926 (Box 1)
      - September 27, 1927-October 31, 1927 (Box 1)
      - October 31, 1927-March 3, 1928 (Box 1)
      - July 22, 1929-December 16, 1936 (Box 1)
      - April 15, 1937-October 1, 1941 (Box 1)
    - Organization Committee
      - April 21, 1913-May 9, 1913 (Box 1)
      - May 10, 1913-September 10, 1913 (Box 1)
      - December 16, 1913 (Box 1)
      - January 12, 1914-August 4, 1915 (Box 1)
    - Annual Meeting
      - Correspondence, 1925, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Correspondence, 1926, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Menus, 1923-1926 (Box 1)
      - Minutes, 1926 (Box 1)
  - Reports
    - Annual Reports
      - 1914 (Box 1)
      - 1915 (Box 1)
      - 1916 (Box 1)
      - 1917 (Box 1)
      - 1918, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - 1920, 3 folders (Box 1)
      - 1921, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - 1921 (Draft copy with illustrations in 2 volumes, "The Lincoln Highway, Eighth Year of Progress, Nineteen Twenty-One.") (Port Port. 1)
      - Undated draft (Box 1)
    - Technical Committee Meeting Reports/Minutes
      - Resolutions, 1920 List of Members (Box 1)
      - Meeting Minutes, 1920 "Ideal" Section (Box 1)
      - Meeting Minutes, 1921-1922 "Ideal" Section (Box 1)
      - April 23, 1921-September 17, 1921 "Ideal" Section (Box 1)
      - November 1, 1921-July 15, 1922 "Ideal" Section (Box 1)
      - July 15, 1922 "Ideal" Section (Box 1)
      - November 3, 1922-May 1, 1923 "Ideal" Section (Box 1)
      - October 31, 1923-November 22, 1923 "Ideal" Section (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous Reports
      - 1916 (Box 1)
      - 1920 (Box 1)
      - 1921-1922 (Box 1)
      - 1922 (Box 1)
      - Undated (Box 1)
      - An "Ideal Section" on the Lincoln Highway, ca. 1919 (Box 1)
  - Bulletins
    - Bulletins from Secretary's Office
      - September 19, 1912-August 15, 1913 (Box 1)
    - Directors' Bulletins
      - January 26, 1914-April 6, 1914 (Box 1)
      - April 13, 1914-July 14, 1914 (Box 1)
      - July 27, 1914-February 10, 1915 (Box 1)
    - To Directors, Officers, and Founders
      - January 22, 1916-April 12, 1916 (Box 1)
      - April 15, 1916-July 1, 1916 (Box 1)
      - July 15, 1916-December 23, 1916 (Box 1)
      - June 23, 1919-December 22, 1921 (Box 1)
      - January 17, 1922-January 31, 1922 (Box 1)
      - February 4, 1922-April 10, 1922 (Box 1)
      - April 11, 1922-June 12, 1922 (Box 1)
      - June 19, 1922-August 11, 1922 (Box 1)
      - August 21, 1922-October 9, 1922 (Box 1)
      - October 16, 1922-October 23, 1922 (Box 1)
      - November 6, 1922-December 26, 1922 (Box 1)
      - January 3, 1923-April 9, 1923 (Box 1)
      - April 16, 1923-July 2, 1923 (Box 1)
      - July 9, 1923-August 27, 1923 (Box 1)
      - September 13, 1923-October 15, 1923 (Box 1)
      - November 5, 1923-December 31, 1923 (Box 1)
      - January 5, 1924-March 9, 1925 (Box 1)
      - March 16, 1925-May 25, 1925 (Box 1)
      - June 1, 1925-July 27, 1925 (Box 1)
      - August 3, 1925-October 12, 1915 (Box 1)
      - October 19, 1925-December 28, 1925 (Box 1)
      - January 5, 1926-March 24, 1926 (Box 1)
      - April 5, 1926-June 14, 1926 (Box 1)
      - June 25, 1926-October 11, 1926 (Box 1)
      - October 20, 1926-December 27, 1926 (Box 1)
  - Legal Documents
    - Founding Documents/Internal Resolutions
      - May 1913-June 1913 (Box 1)
      - August 10, 1913-September 14, 1914 undated (Box 1)
      - August 2, 1926 undated (Box 1)
    - Contracts/Resolutions with States
      - Indiana
        - April 22, 1921-April 26, 1921 undated (Box 1)
      - Utah
        - March 16, 1916-March 21, 1918 (Box 1)
        - July 20, 1920-June 14, 1925 (Box 1)
    - Legislative Documents
      - 1917-1924 undated (Box 1)
    - Financial Statements/Reports
      - May 7, 1913-September 15, 1914 (Box 1)
      - May 5, 1916-November 10, 1927 (Box 1)
    - Hearings/Briefs for Secretary of Agriculture
      - Hearing Before the Secretary of Agriculture. Lincoln Highway in Utah and Nevada. Hart, Dice & Carlson, Shorthand Reporters, Washington, D.C., May 14, 1923 (Box 2)
      - Photocopy LH in Utah, Nevada, pp. i-49 (Box 2)
      - Photocopy LH in Utah, Nevada, pp. 50-99 (Box 2)
      - Photocopy LH in Utah, Nevada, pp. 100-143 (Box 2)
      - A Brief for the Lincoln Highway in Utah and Nevada Addressed to The Secretary of Agriculture, Washington D.C. A Study of Western Road Strategy Designed to Aid in Determining the Road of Most Immediate Importance Connecting Salt Lake City, Utah, with California. Prepared by The National Headquarters, The Lincoln Highway Association, Detroit, Michigan, March 15, 1923.
        - Paperback Copy (Box 5)
        - Roy D. Chapin's Copy (Box 5)
        - Boxed Leather Copy (Box 5)
  - Medals (Box 2)
  - H.C. Ostermann Memorial (Box 2)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series (1912-1929) contains incoming and outgoing correspondence between members of the Lincoln Highway Association, interested individuals and organizations, and federal and state governments. Subseries include: Car Companies, Subscription/Contributions, Federal Government, State Government, Automobile Club of Southern California, and Miscellaneous. Three subseries cover correspondence regarding specific areas along the Lincoln Highway and include the "Ideal" Section, Seiberling Section, and Utah/Nevada. Within the each subseries, the correspondence is organized by correspondent and then chronologically. This series is not comprehensive and does not contain all the collections' correspondence. Some correspondence remains in other series in order to provide context for the themes and topics addressed within the correspondence.
  The Car Companies subseries (1912-1917) includes correspondence between major automobile companies, their representatives, and board members of the Lincoln Highway Association. Key players include Henry Ford and the Ford Motor Company, Will J. Dobyns from the Fisher Automobile Company, Hudson Motor Car Company, Packard Motor Car Company, Union Carbine Company, the American Automobile Association, and Austin Bement, Carl G. Fisher, Henry B. Joy, and Arthur R. Pardington. The majority of correspondence relates to solicitation of funds, donations, subscriptions, discussions of the philosophy of the highway, and some early organizational business between the future board members.
  The subseries Subscriptions/Contributions (1912-1919) provides records of money donated to the cause of building the Lincoln Highway. This is important financial information that is lacking from official organizational records. This series can help to show what individuals and businesses were interested in promoting the Lincoln Highway as well as answer other financial questions regarding donations to the Association. Individuals, representatives of industry, and board members of the Lincoln Highway Association author the letters throughout this subseries. There are also several examples of blank subscription forms.
  The Federal Government (1912-1923) and State Government (1913-1923) subseries deal with exchanges between the Association and the respective governments. Topics for both governments include seeking support for the highway project, both legislatively and financially. Correspondence from the Federal government includes letters between the Department of Agriculture, Secretary of War H.L. Scott, Colonel Theodore Roosevelt, and President William Howard Taft. Letters are present from state governors and agencies in New York, New Jersey, Indiana, Illinois, Nebraska, Utah, and California.
  The Automobile Club of Southern California (1915) has a small exchange of letters between Fred Baker, President of the club in 1915 and Henry B. Joy discussing the Lincoln Highway project. The Automobile Club of Southern California was one of the earliest auto clubs in the country. The organization was active in promoting the cause of the Lincoln Highway, other roads, and published maps and road guides for motorists.
  The Miscellaneous subseries (1912-1925) contains correspondence between Association members including Austin Bement, Carl G. Fisher, Henry B. Joy, individual supporters, and steel and concrete companies.
  The "Ideal" Section subseries (1920-1929) deals with the construction, problems, and issues surrounding the Lincoln Highway between Dyer and Schererville, Lake County, Indiana. Letters are arranged by correspondent and include Vice-President and Secretary of the LHA Austin Bement, Edsel Ford, the landscrape architect Jens Jensen, and the consulting engineer W. G. Thompson.